<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Travcut Educational Consult</title>
    <description>Travcutedu's blog,Give information about schools in the United States of America,Securing admissions into colleges in USA</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4001/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4001/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 12:04:26 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 12:04:26 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Benefits of Studying in the USA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. High Ranked Institutions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s well known that many of the best universities in the world are located in the United States of America. In fact, according to the QS World University Rankings 2015/2016, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2015#sorting=rank+region=+country=+faculty=+stars=false+search=&quot;&gt;half of the top ten best universities in the world&lt;/a&gt; are located in the US. The United States of America is home to hundreds of prestigious universities and colleges such as Harvard University, Stanford, Princeton, Yale, University of Chicago and a host of others. No matter the state in US you wish to study, you will have plenty of amazing choices to upgrade your education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Cost of Living:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on where you choose to study in the US, the cost of living can vary considerably. Living costs in the US can often be lower than those in other popular study destinations. Suburban and rural areas in the South and Midwest generally have the lowest cost of living, with big urban centers like New York City entailing considerably higher living expenses (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.topuniversities.com/universities/new-york-university-nyu/&quot;&gt;New York University&lt;/a&gt; gives an average annual estimate of $24,000). To supplement your income, you may like to seek &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.topuniversities.com/student-info/studying-abroad/can-you-work-part-time-us-student-visa&quot;&gt;part-time work on campus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Choose from a Variety of Programs:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are over 4,000 US universities offering undergraduate and post graduate degrees, there are various opportunities to combine various subjects as ‘majors’ and ‘minors’ in the undergraduate level.  The United States is the place you go if you want to experiment with different classes and subjects. There is no other country in the world where you can find such a diverse range of programs and flexibility as you can find in the US. You will be able to study some of the most innovative subjects and interact with well-known scholars who will guide you during your study years. The huge number of US universities and colleges also means you have many options when it comes to choosing the kind of experience you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Extension of your F-1 Visa Status for the Optional Practical Training (OPT):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optional Practical Training (OPT) is a temporary employment that is directly related to an F-1 student’s major area of study. Undergraduates and graduates holding the F-1 visa are permitted by the United States Citizenship and Immigration Services (USCIS) to work for one year on a student visa towards getting practical training to complement their education. Eligible students can apply to receive up to 12 months of OPT employment authorization before completing their academic studies and/or after completing their academic studies. On March 11, 2016, the Department of Homeland Security published a final rule allowing certain F-1 students who receive science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) degrees, and who meet other specified requirements, to apply for a 24-month extension of their post-completion OPT, giving STEM graduates a total of 36 months of OPT. The OPT will enable those with the student visa to receive practical training that will complement their education and also boost their curriculum vitae/resume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Improve the Prospects for your Graduate Career:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;he skills attained by studying a postgraduate degree in the US will strengthen your CV and certainly help you stand out amongst those who have obtained a postgraduate qualification from other countries. You’ll be acquiring knowledge at a higher level than what you studied during your bachelor’s degree. With a postgraduate qualification on your CV, securing a good graduate job is more likely, and the possibility of attracting a higher salary is increased. This will leave you feeling confident that the time and money invested in your postgraduate education was actually worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/assets/img/blog/post/benefits-of-studing-in-usa.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Meet People from all Around the Globe:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States is the most diverse country in the whole world. You can experience the most vibrant campus life in the institutions here. Given the fact that the US is the top choice for most international students, you should expect to meet people from all corners of the world on a daily basis. You are sure to make lifelong connections and return home knowing that you’ve got new friendships that will last a lifetime.  By attending a US university, you will get the chance to experience one of the most interesting cultures, and also interact with other students from all corners of the world and become truly international. It is the passion of most young minds to visit and settle in the US, and the easiest way of making that passion a reality is by traveling to the US for your studies. You can live on the university campus, join sports teams, clubs, and have all the amazing experiences you’ve been yearning for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. More Relevance in the Job Market:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a known fact that US universities have a great reputation and are well-known for the quality of their education.  Hence, it’s not surprising that companies are excited to welcome young people with US University degrees.  Companies all over the world give reference first to job seekers who have earned a degree from a University in the US compared to other countries. By studying in the US, you will make the first step towards a successful international career. During your student years, you will also have the opportunity to gain experience in your field of study through the Optional Practical Training program. Studying abroad at a US university is perfect preparation for an international workplace, giving you the international experience which is sought by many employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Gain a New Perspective on the World:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s good to note that studying abroad is an interesting life experience altogether, more so, studying in a place so complex and varied as the United States is even more fascinating. Studying in the US has helped many international students get out of their comfort zone, become more open-minded, and broaden their horizons. Studying in the US will be a meaningful experience that will expand your view of the world. You will not only grow professionally, but also personally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Process your Admissions to a US School with Ease:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processing your admission to a University in the USA is not as difficult as many people portray. At &lt;strong&gt;Travcut Educational Consult&lt;/strong&gt;, your application is done with ease and less worries. We will help you successfully process your admission into a school in the US; we will also assist you with your visa application and put you through all the processes involved. For more information, visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.travcutedu.com.ng&quot;&gt;www.travcutedu.com.ng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4001/admission/2017/08/23/benefits-of-studying-in-the-usa.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4001/admission/2017/08/23/benefits-of-studying-in-the-usa.html</guid>
        
        <category>Benefits</category>
        
        <category>Study</category>
        
        <category>Admission</category>
        
        <category>Universities</category>
        
        <category>United States</category>
        
        
        <category>Admission</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQs) about Studying in the USA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. There are so many schools in the USA, how do I decide which school to apply to?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Choosing where and what to study in America can seem like a big project. Research your options and define your priorities. Know what you want and go for it. To help you narrow it down to the best options for you, Travcut Educational Consult offers a range of universities and degree options that reflects the wide choice on offer in USA. Our skilled and experienced advisors can talk you through your options and help you come to the best decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Can you work while studying in the US?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With permission of the International Student Office, international students may work on campus up to 20 hours/week in their first year and can apply to work off-campus in subsequent years. International students are allowed to work part-time during the semester and full-time during holidays, on campus. You are not allowed to work off campus until after your 1st year and then only with special permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. When will the Tuition fees be paid?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are schools which accept part payment of tuition fees before arrival whereas, some do no accept any payment until the student arrives at the school. We look out for those schools where you will be making payment on arrival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. What’s the difference between a college and a university?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colleges offer mostly undergraduate degrees while universities offer undergraduate and graduate degrees, although the terms are often used interchangeably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please note:&lt;/strong&gt; Based on our research over the years, the US embassy in Nigeria recognizes an I-20/Admission letter from a University more than a College. Visas are easily granted to students going to Universities than those going to Colleges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Can I get financial aids/scholarships to study in a University in the US?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many universities in the United States give out scholarships as well as financial aid that are open to international students. Scholarships are usually grants for which repayment is not required, and they are based on academic or sporting merit. All types of academic scholarships are extremely competitive and require outstanding academic records (80% aggregate). Sports Scholarships require good grades and demonstrated excellence in sport, usually at the provincial or national level. Financial aid is based on financial need, but may also be based on academic merit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/assets/img/blog/post/faq-about-usa.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. How can I apply for a scholarship?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for you to apply for scholarships, you will have to fill in financial aid forms for each university you apply to.  Scholarships are usually sourced from the institution at which you enroll, and not from outside bodies or philanthropies.  There is very little aid available through such (philanthropists) sources for individual applicants, and it is usually earmarked for advanced graduate (Master’s and PhD program) students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. How long does it take to be accepted into an American University?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That depends on which universities you are applying to. Some universities have earlier deadlines than others, and some have rolling admissions which means they accept applications until they are full. Universities with a regular decision deadline usually respond to students in the end of March and students must confirm their admission by May 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. What is an academic year?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each college and university determines its own academic year. Thus, this will vary depending on where you study. The academic year in the United States usually begins in late August or early September and continues through May or June. Each year is divided into terms. Typically, a school will have either two terms per academic year (semesters), three terms (trimesters) or four terms (quarters). Many schools divide the calendar year into four “quarters”, and then designate three of those quarters (usually fall, winter, and spring) as the academic year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. I want to study in the United States. How do I get started?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get started by doing some research through any of the search engines like Google and choose the school that suits you best. You can as well contact Travcut Educational Consult, a leading international educational agency in Nigeria with many years of professional student placement, scholarship assistance and visa counseling service.  Find out more about us at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.travcutedu.com.ng&quot;&gt;www.travcutedu.com.ng&lt;/a&gt; or call +234 818 7220 776&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. How can I ask a question that is not answered here?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can’t find the answer to your question, you can contact our professional, helpful team through phone on +234 818 7220 776 or WhatsApp @ +234 906 8606 770 or send us a mail via &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:info@travcutedu.com.ng&quot;&gt;info@travcutedu.com.ng&lt;/a&gt;. We are experts in American university’s admission and entry requirements for international students.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4001/admission/2017/08/22/frequently-asked-questions-about-studing-in-the-usa.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4001/admission/2017/08/22/frequently-asked-questions-about-studing-in-the-usa.html</guid>
        
        <category>FAQs</category>
        
        <category>Questions</category>
        
        <category>Admission</category>
        
        <category>Universities</category>
        
        <category>United States</category>
        
        
        <category>Admission</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>10 Questions To Ask When Choosing A University  To Study In The United States</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons people choose a university to study at in the United States- from fantastic architectural designs, beautiful websites to how many familiar faces they would meet on getting admitted. However, choosing the right school can be quite challenging, the complexity of  choosing which  program to study, and  the academic standard of the institution are some of those factors that need to be considered. Nevertheless, the choice of a right school is still dependent on your goals and motive behind getting tertiary  education. 
An institution might be appropriate for one person and not be for another.  Setting one’s priorities first are the key to choosing the right school. In doing that, following the steps below would help&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What are my academic goals?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain schools have designed their programs to specifically suite some line of discipline. These are the first set of colleges to consider when going for a pre-professional education. 
A School of Engineering for example will likely focus more on matters related to the field by adequately furnishing the student with cutting edge information relevant to their career in the future. It will also provide an avenue to meet and build long lasting and meaningful relationships with those who would end up being colleagues in the field in the future.
In picking programs within humanities, consider if the institution has a high ranking for that particular course.  Colleges are better at offering one program than the other. Ensure the institution you’re choosing has a high standard and rank high in that field.
Some career required specific training to fit into them in the future. Do you require training to fit into a particular career (professional career) or do you need to be generally equipped for any career of choice in the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Will the university provide for me a working experience while I study?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go for schools  that have programs and the opportunity of solid work experience intertwined in it. 
Some institutions have designed internship programs to equip students. This knowledge you acquire on the field is quite important to boost your confidence in your career. The experience of work always serves as leverage when you begin to work in an organization in the future&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Does the institution have the right program to equip me for my long term and career goals?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get the best out of an institution through the choice of programs that will equip you for your long term goal in life. This is crucial. An institution can have many things to its advantage but may not necessarily provide the program you have in mind or something close to it. Your long term goal shouldn’t however be sacrificed for a university experience that will leave you unaccomplished in later years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Does the University provide support for foreign students?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schools provide adequate support for international students more than the other. These are factors to consider. If you are considering a program in a university that doesn’t have adequate support offered foreign students, you may need to review the decision. 
Moving into another country entirely comes with its own challenges.  You are faced with new culture, lifestyle and many more. You need all the help you can get. Some institution may be willing to go the extra mile in assisting you to procure your students visa. Often, schools with higher number of foreign students tend to provide better support for those studying abroad. Also, being in an environment where you have a significant population of students from other nationalities tend to be of added advantage. Usually, there is a support group whereby help is provided for such students since they all tend to face similar challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Will the school environment give me a memorable experience?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go for a school that will give you not just the book experience but also the pleasure of  enjoying social activities like  clubs, society, and other interactive group that will add to your academic experience.
A college within a city thriving with a good measure of social activities is also better than in a town where there is little to nothing. The memories of the people you meet, the places you’ve been to, are some of those things that will make the schooling worth the while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/assets/img/blog/post/things-to-consider.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. What are those things you require in an institution?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic things you require in an institution would still be those things that draw you to the colleges you pick within your first five choices. Some of these reasons could be based on logical reasoning or personal sentiments, and may not be categorized as right or wrong in choosing an ideal college for you. However, in the situation whereby these reasons are clashing with your academic goals, you may have to review them.
What you want in an institution could be an affordable accommodation within the school facility. This perhaps is one crucial factor to consider when studying abroad. Most schools will make adequate accommodation facility for students from other nationality. But if you would be taking up an apartment within the city or town where the college is located, you may have to consider the cost of living since this varies from one city to another. The cost of living in Los Angeles is quite different from that of Seattle. Based on budgets, these are some factors to consider, where you schooled is where you live, though, temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Do I meet the academic requirement to enroll in the university?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeting the academic requirement of an institution or the course of study is a factor to consider when choosing which university to enroll. Requirement may vary from one institution to another. Not meeting a requirement may mean you would have to look for something close to what your original choice may have been.
Do you need to sit for a preliminary test, exam or an interview before admission? What are the documents required to tender before your admission? Are they all available?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Does my budget cover for the tuition of the school?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Budget is an aspect to give thought to when making a choice. Does your budget cover the school of your choice?  It is not enough for your savings to barely cover just a semester of the academic year. Getting enrolled in some universities can be quite expensive and what you have budgeted for your schooling may not be able to cover for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Does the institution provides an avenue to interact one –on one with supervisors and encourages it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This form of support goes a long way in helping students accomplish their goals.There is much knowledge to be gleaned through interaction with supervisors. It makes the common challenges of schooling easier to surmount
Institutions that encourage and provide moral and other form of support to students create a better environment for study&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Does the school provide scholarship for foreign students?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have scholarship in mind while you contemplate studying abroad but if your budget is drawing you back and the school is not providing the opportunity for scholarship, you may have to opt for another one. 
There are many institutions that liaise with organizations that give scholarships to both local and foreign students. Look out for these universities within the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4001/admission/2017/02/26/things-to-consider-when-choosing-a-college-abroad.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4001/admission/2017/02/26/things-to-consider-when-choosing-a-college-abroad.html</guid>
        
        <category>Questions</category>
        
        <category>Study</category>
        
        <category>University</category>
        
        
        <category>Admission</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Understanding US Admission Cycle into Universities</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After carefully going through the various universities in United States and settling with a choice, you may be wondering when exactly to apply to that University you have chosen. Many of the universities in the U.S operate a tri-semester cycle: the Spring, Summer and Fall. It is important to know when to apply to the University of your choice and be aware also of the deadline of application.Each of these semesters has the specific deadline as stipulated by each institution on when the enrollment closes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fall semester which lasts for 13 weeks is the first in the academic year. Starting in august, the semester extends through to the month of Dec and sometimes till mid-Jan. The usual process is for students to begin the process of their admission a four to  three month  before the beginning of the US academic year so as to secure a place in the university.  Most universities only admit student at the beginning of the fall semester (also known as autumn semester) which is the beginning of the academic year.
The spring semester has duration of about 16 to 18 weeks and begins in the first to second week in Jan. Most universities require students coming in during the spring semester to have begun the processing of their admission by October  of the previous 
.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some universities, the deadline for enrolment is around September to October before the commencement of the spring semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summer semester which starts in the month of June is the shortest and the last before the commencement of a new academic year.
Admission into university during this period depends on the school and the department. Some department may or may not be able to take in students during this period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/assets/img/blog/post/usa-admission-cycle.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Admission Timeline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the beginning of the Summer Semester which is the last of the academic year, you should have researched your options as regard Universities of your choice. By the beginning of the Fall Semester which is in August, you should have prepared your application papers and the process should begin. Most Application closes by Nov – Jan after which schools begin to send replies to students in between the month of February to March. Subsequent months before school resumes for another academic year provides ample opportunity to apply for scholarship if need be, students visa  and prepare for departure as a new year begins in August (the Fall/Autumn  Semester).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fall is the ideal time for foreign students to enroll in the university. This is because it gives enough time to apply for student’s visa and scholarship. Starting the process of admission early is the best when enrolling. The application timeline will provide detailed steps needed to be taken and when to carry them out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities in the United State offer flexibility in their application process. You don’t have to wait for the application to be opened for the semester to begin to apply. Through three plans- the Early plan, the Regular admission and the Rolling admission these institutions make it possible to be enrolled at specific time in the academic 
Provided there are vacant seats, the Rolling admission plan allows you to apply in the University you have chosen.  The Regular admission provides opportunity to apply to the university within the application timeline for each of the three semesters, the Fall, Spring, and Summer semesters. Whereas, the early admission gives the student an opportunity to apply ahead and fix his admission before the regular admission begins into the institution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4001/admission/2017/02/25/understanding-US-admission-cycle-into-universities.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4001/admission/2017/02/25/understanding-US-admission-cycle-into-universities.html</guid>
        
        <category>Admission</category>
        
        <category>Universities</category>
        
        <category>United States</category>
        
        
        <category>Admission</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
